Part 4. You will hear part of a lecture to medical students
about playing music to patients who are in hospital for surgery.
First, you have some time to look at questions 31 to 40.
Now listen carefully and answer questions 31 to 40.
Today's lecture is about studies that look at how music therapy can be used to help patients
who undergo surgery. Now, most people undergo a surgical procedure at some point in their lives,
and more than 51 million operations are performed annually in the USA.
But there's no escaping the fact that most patients feel uncomfortable following surgery.
They may have difficulty mobilizing, and even sitting up in bed can feel too much.
They may also be negatively affected by having their routine disturbed. You know,
like if they can't do the things they normally do, or have to devote a lot of time to appointments,
such as physiotherapy, to aid their recovery. Currently, the main strategy for improving
recovery is medication to control pain. And this can be administered to patients in the short,
medium, or longer term, depending on the extent of their surgery.
But music is still not an everyday part of the post-surgical phase,
despite a wealth of relevant studies supporting its potential in recovery.
Earlier this year, a research team set out to assess all the available evidence
so that they could highlight the potential for music in surgical recovery.
They identified nearly 100 trials involving a total of 7,000 patients who were played recorded
music as part of their post-operative care. The researchers then looked at what impact
the music had on the patients. They discovered that patients who had been played music
reported feeling happier and more satisfied in the post-operative phase,
and the length of their stay was shorter than for patients who had not listened to any music.
The researchers also explored the patient's choice of music, and their findings showed
that a wide variety of music styles was evident. However, a common factor was that the chosen music
had a calming quality. Some of the patients listened to music with headphones,
but it was quiet enough not to prevent them from being able to communicate with nurses and other
staff. More often, though, the mode of delivery was by what are known as music pillows. These
broadcast sound that is only audible to the person lying on them. The research involved
testing music before, during, or after operations, or a combination. Some patients listened to the
music just once a day, while others had several episodes a day.
When asked to report their experience of listening to music, surgical patients said that either they
had no feelings of anxiety at any point, or those feelings were only slight. Patients who hadn't
listened to music, on the other hand, reported higher levels of dissatisfaction. This feedback
from all of the patients was then cross-checked against their medical notes, and in every case,
those who were given music to listen to didn't need as much medication to ease their pain
as those patients who weren't played music. The type of music, patient choice and timing
before, during, or after the surgery didn't make much difference, and it even worked when
patients were played music under general anesthetic, although the positive effects
were greater when patients were awake. All the evidence suggests that music has a positive
effect on post-operative patients, but it's not entirely clear how or why this is the case.
A lot of people listen to music in daily life as a way to relax and forget their problems,
but the researchers came to the conclusion that it worked on patients by distraction.
I suppose it was something familiar and gave them something they could control.
The researchers say there is now sufficient research to demonstrate that music should be
available to all patients undergoing operations. They say patients should be able to choose what
they'd like to listen to, and if they prefer, recordings taken from nature can be just as good
as music. Surgical teams may prefer patients to listen to music before the procedure or as soon
as they arrive back onto the ward. Clearly, there's more to learn about this area, and the
team now plan to focus their next research on the most appropriate volume to play the music at,
and I look forward to reading the results of their study. It will be interesting to see that if it's
That is the end of part four. You now have one minute to check your answers to part four.